Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we learn a little bit more
about how to keep our heart healthy.
And we start with ways to
improve our heart rate variability.
Everyone feel for your pulse.
Hold out your hand, thumb up,
and feel for the knobby bone
at the top of your wrist.
Okay, now,
slide your hand down
and across the front
of your wrist.
Feel those, like,
strands of spaghetti?
Those are the tendons
in your wrist.
If you press lightly
between the knobby bone
and that first tendon,
you should feel your pulse.
Got it?
Okay,
now what we're going to do
is feel what happens
to our pulse
when we take a deep breath.
We're going to try it twice.
Try to feel what happens
to your pulse when you inhale
and when you exhale.
All right, here we go,
slow inhale.
(inhales)
Slow exhale.
(exhales)
One more time.
In.
Out.
What happened when you
breathed in and breathed out?
You should have felt your pulse
speed up when you inhaled
and slow down
when you exhaled.
That's called
heart rate variability,
a measure of the control
our vagus nerve has
over our heart.
And it's a good thing.
A healthy heart
is not a metronome.
Low heart rate variability
predicts greater risk
of heart disease and death
from several causes.
High-risk patients with
low variability in heart rate
have twice the risk
of dying prematurely.
Is there anything we can do
to positively impact
heart rate variability?
Voluntary slow breathing,
at about six breaths per minute,
is a technique that's been used
for thousands of years
as an essential part
of many meditative
and relaxation practices.
It can benefit several heart
rate variability parameters,
offering a low-tech,
low-cost technique.
Speaking of low-tech, low-cost:
What about exercise?
Aerobic training
at least twice a week
positively influences
heart nerve control.
What about what we eat?
Those eating plant-based diets
have better
overall heart rate variability.
Vegetarians, for example,
don't tend to have only
better blood pressure,
cholesterol, triglycerides,
and blood sugars,
they also have
better heart rate variability.
The vagus nerve toning effects
of plant-based diets
may help explain part of
their cardioprotective effect.
Any plants in particular?
While no significant association
was seen
between heart rate
variability measures
and the intake of fruits
and vegetables in general,
the consumption
of green leafy vegetables
seems to stand out,
perhaps helping to explain
why eating just a half serving
of greens a day
may cut our risk of having a
heart attack by up to 67%!
In our next story,
How Not to Die from heart disease.
The most likely reason most of our
loved ones will die is heart disease.
It's still up to each of us to make
our own decisions as to what to eat
and how to live — but we should
make these choices consciously,
educating ourselves about the predictable
consequences of our actions.
Atherosclerosis, hardening of
the arteries, begins in childhood.
By age 10, the arteries of nearly all kids
raised on the standard American diet
already have fatty streaks —
the first stage of the disease.
Then the plaques start
forming in our 20s,
get worse in our 30s and
then can start killing us off.
In our heart it's called a heart attack;
in our brain it can manifest as a stroke.
So if there is anyone watching
this older than age 10,
then the choice isn't whether or not
to eat healthy to prevent heart disease,
it's whether or not you want to reverse
the heart disease you likely already have.
Is that even possible?
When researchers took people with
heart disease and put them on
the kind of plant-based diet
followed by populations
that did not get epidemic
heart disease,
their hope was that it might slow the disease
process down, maybe even stop it.
But instead something
miraculous happened.
The disease started to reverse,
to get better.
As soon as patients stopped
eating artery-clogging diets,
their bodies were able to start
dissolving some of the plaque away,
opening up arteries without
drugs, without surgery,
suggesting their bodies
wanted to heal all along,
but were just never
given the chance.
That improvement in blood flow to
the heart muscle itself (on the left)
was after just three weeks eating healthy.
Let me share with you what's been
called the best kept secret in medicine.
The best kept secret in medicine is that
sometimes, given the right conditions,
the body can heal itself.
You know if you whack your shin
really hard on a coffee table,
it can get all red, hot, painful,
swollen, inflamed,
but will heal naturally if
you just stand back
and let your body work its magic.
But what if you kept whacking your
shin in the same place day after day,
in fact three times a day
(breakfast, lunch, and dinner).
It'd never heal!
You'd go to your doctor and
be like, "Oh, my shin hurts,"
and the doctor would be like,
"No problem," whip out their pad,
write you a prescription
for painkillers.
You're still whacking your
shin three times a day.
Oh, it still really hurts like heck,
but oh, feels so much better
with those pain pills on board.
Thank heavens for
modern medicine.
It's like when people take nitroglycerine
for crushing chest pain,
tremendous relief, but you're not doing
anything to treat the underlying cause.
Our body wants to come
back to health if we let it.
But if we keep re-damaging ourselves
three times a day, we may never heal.
One of the most amazing things
I learned in all my medical training
was that within about 15 years
of stopping smoking,
your lung cancer risk approaches
that of a lifelong nonsmoker.
Isn't that amazing?
Your lungs can clear
out all that tar,
and eventually, it's almost, as if
you never started smoking at all.
And every morning of our smoking
life that healing process started until —
Wham! Our first cigarette of the day,
reinjuring our lungs with every puff,
just like we can reinjure our
arteries with every bite,
when all we had to do all
along—the miracle cure—
is just stand back, get out of the way,
stop re-damaging ourselves,
and let our bodies natural healing
processes bring us back towards health.
The human body is a
self-healing machine.
Sure, you could choose moderation—
hit yourself with a smaller hammer—
but why beat yourself up at all?
I don't tell my smoking patients
to cut down to half-a-pack a day,
I tell them to quit.
Sure, a half pack is better
than two packs a day,
but we should try to only put
healthy things in our mouths.
We've known about this for decades:
American Heart Journal, 1977.
Cases like Mr. F.W. here —
heart disease so bad
he couldn't even make it to the mailbox,
but started eating healthier,
and a few months later he was
climbing mountains, no pain.
There are these fancy new anti-angina,
anti-chest pain drugs out now.
They cost thousands of dollars a year,
but at the highest dose, they may be
able to prolong exercise duration,
as long as 33 and a half seconds.
It does not look like those
choosing the drug route
will be climbing mountains
anytime soon.
See, plant-based diets aren't
just safer and cheaper.
They can work better because you're
treating the actual cause of the disease.
Finally today,
when doctors withhold dietary treatment
options from cardiac patients,
they are violating the cornerstone of
medical ethics, informed consent.
When he was a surgeon at
the Cleveland Clinic,
Dr. Caldwell Esselstyn published a controversial
paper in the American Journal of Cardiology.
Heart bypass operations
carry significant risks,
including the potential to cause further
heart damage, stroke, brain dysfunction.
Angioplasty isn’t much better, also carrying
significant mortality and morbidity,
and often doesn’t work, in
terms of decreasing risk
of subsequent heart
attack or death.
So, it seems we have
an enormous paradox.
The disease that is the leading
killer of men and women
in Western civilization
is largely untreated.
The benefits of the invasive procedures
are at best temporary,
with most patients eventually
succumbing to their disease.
In cancer we call
that palliative care,
where we just kind of
throw up our hands,
throw in the towel and give up actually
trying to treat the disease.
So why does this juggernaut of
invasive procedures persist?
Well one reason is that performing
surgical interventions
has the potential for
enormous financial reward.
That’s considered one of the barriers to the
practice of preventive cardiology -
adequate return.
Diet and lifestyle interventions
loses money for the physician.
Although the practice of preventive
cardiology is not as lucrative,
this article was hoping to nudge
cardiologists in that direction
by appealing to less
tangible benefits.
Another barrier is doctors don’t
think patients want it.
Physician surveys show that doctors often
don’t even bring up diet and lifestyle options,
assuming that patients
would prefer for example
to be on cholesterol-lowering drugs
every day for the rest of their lives.
That may be true for some, but
it’s up to the patient to decide.
According to the official
AMA Code of Medical Ethics,
physicians are supposed to disclose all
relevant medical information to patients.
The patient’s right of self-decision
can be effectively exercised
only if the patient possesses enough
information to enable an informed choice.
The physician's obligation is to present the
medical facts accurately to the patient.
For example, before starting someone at moderate
risk on a cholesterol-lowering statin drug,
a physician might ideally
say something like
“You should know that for
folks in your situation,
the number of individuals who
must be treated with a statin
to prevent one death from a cardiovascular
event such as a heart attack or stroke—
is generally between
60 and 100,
which means that if I treated
60 people in your position,
1 might benefit
and 59 would not.
As these numbers show, it is
important for you to know
that most of the people who take a
statin will not benefit from doing so
and, moreover, that statins
can have side effects,
such as muscle pain, liver
damage, upset stomach,
even in people who do not
benefit from the medication.
I am giving you this information so that
you can weigh the risks and benefits
of drugs versus diet and then
make an informed decision.”
Yet how many physicians
have these kinds
of frank and open discussions
with their patients?
Non-disclosure of medical
information by doctors,
that kind of paternalism is supposed
to be a thing of the past,
but now physicians are supposed
to honor informed consent,
unless the patient's in a coma
or something or it's an emergency.
But too many physicians continue
to treat their patients
as if…they were unconscious.
At the end of this long roundtable
discussion on angioplasty and stents,
the editor-in-chief of the
American Journal of Cardiology
reminded the participants of an
important fact to place it all in context.
Atherosclerosis is
due to high cholesterol,
which is due to poor
dietary choices,
and so if we all existed
on a plant-based diet,
we would not have even
needed this discussion.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.